Neil: I'm Neil Cox.
I am a consultant within
Capita Consulting.
A consultant doing lots of
projects and program management.
I've had a variety of different
roles throughout my career.
Project management world it's really
good to get close to the outputs
that you're looking to deliver.
You know, it really is exciting just
to see that change and transformation
piece of work just, just going from
an idea at the start to whatever
you have to deliver afterwards.
But as you get more and more complex
through your work, being able
to do some more bigger strategic
roles are also so valuable because
you'll focus more on outcomes.
And how can you make a business
change or, or really drive outcomes
into a community or a piece of work.
Yeah, I've been a project manager
for around about 18 years.
What is really good is projects can
stem from being very short and snappy
you know even a few days -- spending
a week on something -- to some
other projects, which are much more
complex and they take much longer.
But what that gives you is variety.
My key responsibilities as a project
manager have to be running that
project on a day-to-day basis.
So we'll have a project board, or
we will have a senior responsible
owner or program manager.
They'll be turning to you to
say, can you run this project?
And you then need to own it from
cradle to grave from start to finish.
There will always be people on hand to
help with questions or pointers if you're
unsure with things, but it's yours and
you need to run with it and operate it.
And that goes through all of the
aspects of it, all of the steps
in the entire project cycle.
Or if you're using Prince 2 or Agile,
which whichever model that you're using,
you've got an opportunity then took to
own each one of those steps going through.
This day and age, you can't afford to
have -- depending on how big the project
is -- a dedicated project manager who
just manages the compliance, the risks,
the plans, the finances, et cetera.
Often you've got to get stuck in as well.
So be able to lead from the
front and be able to roll up your
sleeves, get involved with the
deliverables that need to take place.
I myself, you know, whether it's writing,
doing business requirements, running
workshops, to writing communications, to
stakeholder engagement, to doing warranty
calls or, or health check calls, you
end up getting involved with everything.
On a day-to-day basis, your role is
going to be, it's going to be different
during different phases of a project.
So if you focused just really on the
startup or the initiation part of a
project, you're going to be working
through planning, scheduling, what's
the potential risks and issues.
You can be looking into building a team.
You can be looking into
writing business cases.
You're going to be looking into
what's your project finances.
And all of those are really key outputs
to make sure the project is set up
on the right foot to go forwards.
Once you've got everything up and running,
you'll then move into that delivery phase.
And this is really around getting stuck
in and driving the project forwards
and making sure that that all of those
project activities take place on time,
on cost and to the right quality.
You'll move to the closure phase, which
is very keen to make sure the work
that you've done gets transitioned
very successfully over to the business
as usual, or to whoever's going to
own that project going forwards.
But whilst undertaking all of
those different steps and stages.
You need to make sure you're still
on top of your plans, your risks,
your issues, dependencies, financial
management reporting, and very
critically stakeholder engagement.
How do I work out how to assign
the right roles in my team?
It's a real challenge.
The first step you need to consider
is know what it is you're delivering.
It's not a trick question.
You need to be able to know
your strengths and weaknesses.
During a planning phase at the
start of a project it's key to
bring in experts at the right
point to help with your planning.
There's no point planning and
scoping a, you know, a Microsoft
365 migration or technical project,
if you don't actually know what's
involved at each step along the way.
So, it's quite key, you bring
in an expert when you need
it during the planning phase.
And through that, you can work out
what are all the steps, all the tasks
that you need to deliver throughout
your project and pulling on that
expert, they'll be able to fill
in the blanks that you don't know.
Then, once you've identified all of
those tasks and hopefully with a bit of
your expert around, if you need them,
then you can work out what the right
skill sets to help meet those tasks and
those requirements, you know, sometimes
that can be quite challenging to find
resources to allocate to your project.
And you will end up with the people that
might just be available and then you
need to match up skillset to expertise.
So what is the most important
part of the project lifecycle?
I would say it has to be planning.
It's definitely planning because you
want to make sure that your plan, your
project is going to be successful.
And we do a lot of work upfront
before launching a project
to work out what do we need?
When do we need it?
Who do we need?
What do we have to do?
And why are we doing this?
Answering all of those questions upfront
and testing it, validating it, checking
it with peers as well, is really key to
make sure you don't make mistakes later.
You know, if you've got a carpenter coming
in, they will measure twice and cut once.
It's much the same, do the
planning, do it right, check your
planning and then look to engage.
Many times I've been on projects
where the planning hasn't quite
been done to the right level.
And I found myself having to change
and adapt the project later on,
which might push it over budget.
It might make it delayed or it might
just reduce the quality, but if you can't
address all of those items upfront, it
should save you a lot of pain later on.